<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preach'd January XXX. 1684/5 being the fast for the martyrdom of King Charles I of blessed memory / Benjamin Woodroffe ...</title>
            <author>Woodroffe, Benjamin, 1638-1711.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 69 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A66985</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3469</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10607</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12590754</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12590754</idno>
            <idno type="VID">63910</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A66985)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 63910)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 971:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preach'd January XXX. 1684/5 being the fast for the martyrdom of King Charles I of blessed memory / Benjamin Woodroffe ...</title>
                  <author>Woodroffe, Benjamin, 1638-1711.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 38 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.P. for John Blyth, and are to be sold at John Playford's shop ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1685.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  I, --  King of England, 1600-1649 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Fast-day sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:63910:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:63910:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACH'D <hi>JANUARY</hi> XXX. 1684 / 5. BEING THE FAST FOR The Martyrdom of King <hi>Charles</hi> I. of Bleſſed Memory.</p>
            <p>By <hi>BENJAMIN WOODROFFE,</hi> D. D.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>J. P.</hi> for <hi>John Blyth,</hi> and are to be ſold at <hi>John Playford</hi>'s Shop near the <hi>Temple-Church.</hi> 1685.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:63910:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:63910:2"/>
            <head>TO THE SACRED MAJESTY OF King JAMES II.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>'T</hi> Will need no Excuſe, that I ſhould lay any part of my Labours at your Majeſties Feet, where all I can perform is ſo juſt a Debt, and but the natural effect of that Duty I owe, both as <hi>a Subject</hi> to the <hi>beſt of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> and as a <hi>Servant</hi> to the <hi>beſt of Maſters;</hi> nor, I truſt, will it be a <hi>Preſumption</hi> in <hi>One,</hi> who hath had the Honour to ſtand by <hi>Your Majeſty</hi> in <hi>ſome of thoſe Dangers,</hi> where nothing, but that <hi>Divine Providence</hi> which <hi>preſerv'd you for a Crown,</hi> could have been <hi>your Shield,</hi> to preſage, that 'tis for ſome <hi>great and extraordinary Bleſſing to theſe Kingdoms, that you are now ſeated on the Throne.</hi> And it is moſt reaſonable to expect, that, ſo much <hi>natural Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> ſo <hi>great Courage,</hi> and <hi>Bravery of Mind,</hi> ſo ſacred <hi>a Reverence for your Word,</hi> ſo <hi>tender a regard to your Dependants,</hi> ſo <hi>true a Love to your Country,</hi> ſo <hi>invio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable Faith,</hi> and <hi>Allegiance to your Sovereign,</hi> all which made you ſo much <hi>admired</hi> whilſt a <hi>Subject,</hi> ſhould receive the greateſt <hi>Luſtre</hi> from a <hi>Royal Diadem;</hi> for <hi>they</hi> are but the <hi>ſame Vertues You</hi> have ſtill to exerciſe in a <hi>larger Sphere.</hi> If then there was <hi>an Allegiance</hi> you owed, and ſo <hi>exemplari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> paid to your <hi>Royal Brother,</hi> 'tis what is only <hi>exalted</hi> in being now <hi>immediately due</hi> to <hi>none</hi> but <hi>him</hi> who is <hi>King
<pb facs="tcp:63910:3"/> of Kings;</hi> What was then <hi>natural Goodneſs</hi> is now <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency and Mercy;</hi> what was then <hi>Courage and Bravery of Mind,</hi> is now an undaunted <hi>Reſolution</hi> to defend <hi>yours and your Subjects Rights;</hi> what was then the <hi>Reverence</hi> you had for your <hi>ſacred Word,</hi> is now the <hi>perſiſting</hi> in all <hi>your Royal Purpoſes of Grace to your good Subjects;</hi> what was then your <hi>tender regard</hi> to your <hi>Faithful Dependants,</hi> is now, as you are the <hi>Father of your Country,</hi> your <hi>equal Indulgence</hi> to all <hi>your Children;</hi> what was then your true <hi>Love to your Country,</hi> is now advanced into <hi>your Royal Care and Protection of it. Theſe are the things</hi> that will now fill <hi>your Majeſties Thoughts;</hi> and <hi>theſe the great things</hi> that will hereafter be regiſtred by that <hi>Fame</hi> which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſpeaks you ſo <hi>great at home and abroad,</hi> and hath by <hi>your mighty Actions</hi> carried the <hi>Glory</hi> and <hi>Terror</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh Nation</hi> to the <hi>remoteſt Parts of the Univerſe:</hi> and I queſtion not, but the <hi>nearer Parts</hi> of it, <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain,</hi> and thoſe other <hi>your Allies,</hi> who have <hi>ſeen</hi> or <hi>felt your Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage,</hi> will <hi>dread</hi> to <hi>awaken it.</hi> 'Tis only <hi>Treachery</hi> (the heinous nature whereof I treat on in this following Diſcourſe) can diſturb <hi>your Reign:</hi> 'tis <hi>that</hi> which hath done ſo much <hi>Miſchief</hi> already <hi>among us,</hi> and threatens <hi>more</hi> under the <hi>new Name of Trimming. God,</hi> who hath ſet <hi>you</hi> upon the <hi>Throne,</hi> and advanced <hi>your Triumphs</hi> by <hi>Sea and Land</hi> into an <hi>Abſolute Sovereignty in both,</hi> grant that <hi>no Storm</hi> may from <hi>thence</hi> ariſe to infeſt you in <hi>either. Thus Prays,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Majeſties Moſt Dutiful and Obedient Subject, B Woodroffe.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:63910:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>JEREMIAH 3. 8.</bibl>
               <q>But her Treacherous Siſter <hi>Judah</hi> Feared not.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>I Am afraid I ſcarce read my Text without <hi>Offence</hi> to ſome: ſo <hi>ſuspicious</hi> doth <hi>Guilt</hi> make men, that 'tis hard to chooſe the plaineſt piece of Scripture to ſpeak on, on <hi>ſuch Occaſions</hi> as <hi>theſe,</hi> but they think 'tis preſently <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flexion</hi> and <hi>Satyr.</hi> But however, that ought not to deterr the <hi>conſcientious Preacher;</hi> it did not <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remiah,</hi> the Pen-man of theſe Words, from his Duty; and I truſt it ſhall not me from mine: which I take in ſuch a day as this is, a day <hi>of ſo great Rebuke, Indignation,</hi> and <hi>Sorrow,</hi> to be that of our preſent Prophet, <hi>Chap. 1. 8. not to be afraid of their Faces.</hi> Alas! that is ſcarce our caſe, thoſe who are moſt concern'd in the Reproof ſeldom appearing among us on <hi>theſe ſad Solemnities,</hi> and let it reſt as a <hi>Brand of Ignominy,</hi> and <hi>everlaſting Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach,</hi> on their <hi>damn'd Principles</hi> and <hi>helliſh Malice,</hi> that they ſo far ſtill abett the <hi>execrable Treaſon,</hi> as not in ſo <hi>many Years,</hi> after ſo many repeated Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:63910:4"/> of <hi>God's Judgments</hi> on the Nation, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the <hi>Sword,</hi> the <hi>Plague,</hi> and <hi>Fire,</hi> after (if theſe are leſs affecting) ſuch <hi>miraculous Diſcoveries</hi> of their new <hi>Attempts,</hi> their <hi>Bands,</hi> their <hi>Leagues,</hi> their <hi>Covenants,</hi> their <hi>Aſſociations,</hi> and whatever other their <hi>Conſpiracies</hi> ſo plainly laid open, they ſo far countenance the <hi>Villany,</hi> as not to be <hi>hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled for,</hi> or <hi>aſhamed of it.</hi> To theſe Men 'tis my Text addreſſes in the name <hi>of treacherous Judah, i. e.</hi> of thoſe, who under <hi>the Covert</hi> of the <hi>beſt Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> againſt the moſt <hi>manifeſt Tokens of Divine Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance,</hi> as I ſhall by and by have occaſion to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large, go on obſtinately in their wicked Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, and harden themſelves in Miſchief, for that was <hi>Judah</hi>'s Condition, and is the import of the following Meioſis, <hi>feared not,</hi> would be wrought upon by no Inſtruction whatever, would not be warned, take any Example, and reform. And the method I ſhall take in ſpeaking on this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, ſhall be,</p>
            <p n="1">I. To conſider the heinous nature of <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">II. To ſhew what the <hi>Treachery of Iſrael</hi> was.</p>
            <p n="3">III. How her Siſter <hi>Judah</hi> exceeded her in her <hi>Guilt;</hi> and then with reference to what is the Subject of this <hi>Day's Lamentation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">IV. To draw the Parallel in our own Caſe; and</p>
            <p n="5">V. To ſum up all by way of Inference.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:63910:4"/>
            <p>I. Of the heinous nature of <hi>Treachery,</hi> and that in theſe enſuing Particulars.</p>
            <p>1. <hi>Treachery</hi> is a Sin that is moſt oppoſite to the Divine Nature, to the very Being and Eſſence of God himſelf: for <hi>God is Truth and cannot lye, Titus</hi> 1. 2. and every degree of Falſhood is a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting and revolting from him, as he is the Author of Being; 'tis ſo far to unmake his Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, becauſe to make things to be what they are not; to give another Place, Uſe, and Signifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, than he intended his Creatures: beſides, to be <hi>treacherous,</hi> to be <hi>falſe,</hi> to be <hi>hypocritical,</hi> is, what in the Sinner lies, to take away his <hi>Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> becauſe to act as if he had no ſenſe or awe of an <hi>all-ſeeing Eye.</hi> Which is the reaſon, why 'tis ſpoken of in Scripture, as what is ſo hateful to God, Why his <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> as well as his <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Holineſs,</hi> can neither joyn with or approve it.</p>
            <p>2. <hi>Treachery</hi> is a Sin that is moſt oppoſite to the Intereſt of Mankind in general, as 'tis what cuts the Nerves of all Society, wholly deſtroys civil Commerce, undermines all Laws, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts the very Foundations on which Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Order, the Being and Welfare of every Commonwealth, ſubſiſts. <hi>Treachery</hi> is that Sin which gives a Nation one Neck to be beheaded at a blow. Admit <hi>this</hi> in a <hi>State,</hi> and what will
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:63910:5"/> become of the <hi>Rights and Property</hi> either of <hi>Prince</hi> or <hi>People?</hi> Who can call any thing his own, where <hi>Forgery, Subornations,</hi> and <hi>Perjury,</hi> ſet the price on every honeſt man's Head and Fortune?</p>
            <p>Admit <hi>Treachery</hi> in an <hi>Army,</hi> and what will ſignifie the giving either <hi>Word</hi> or <hi>Colours</hi> to be the <hi>diſtinguiſhing Symbols</hi> between them and their Enemies? What the <hi>Command</hi> or <hi>Example</hi> of the wiſeſt and moſt valiant General, if theſe are on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Signals</hi> to the Traitor to turn Sword, Pike, Muſquet, or Canon, upon him? Moſt uncertain muſt the Voice of the Trumpet be, if when that ſounds a Charge, the falſe Heart beats a Retreat? What will it avail to raiſe Forts and lay in Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gazines, if thoſe within the Walls undermine all? If it be only to prepare Bulwarks for others to infeſt us thence?</p>
            <p>Admit <hi>Treachery</hi> in our <hi>Councils,</hi> and what can the Wiſdom of the moſt profound Politician profit?</p>
            <p>Admit <hi>Treachery</hi> into <hi>Court,</hi> and where is the Safety of a Prince among all his Guards?</p>
            <p>Admit <hi>Treachery</hi> on the <hi>Bench,</hi> (Bribery and Partiality are ſo) and how will Laws themſelves be taught to ſpeak Injuſtice and Oppreſſion? What will become either of the <hi>Prerogative of the Prince,</hi> or the <hi>Property of the Subject,</hi> where the <hi>mercenary Judge</hi> makes private Intereſt and Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:63910:5"/> the Rule of his Decrees? Or how muſt this encourage the corrupt Banker, if what is his <hi>Crime,</hi> the Wealth I mean unjuſtly detain'd from the Widow and Orphan, ſhall be his <hi>Protection</hi> and <hi>Defence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Admit <hi>Treachery</hi> in the <hi>Church,</hi> and how will <hi>Conſcience trim</hi> to the Overthrow of all its <hi>Canons?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Treachery,</hi> wherever 'tis, is like the Plague in the Heart, that is therefore moſt fatal, becauſe it ſhews not its ſelf in its natural and outward Tokens. To conclude this Head, If <hi>Treachery</hi> lurk in the Bowels, what will be all our Care in any State whatever? What our Preparations for Peace or War? What our Wealth and Honour? What all our Stores and Proviſions? but like fraughting a goodly Veſſel with the richeſt Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize, giving it ſufficient Ballaſt, fitting up tall and ſtout Maſts, ſpreading abroad the moſt glorious Sails, with all the finery of Flags and Streamers to ſet her off, and after all, boring a Hole in her bottom, whereby ſhe muſt certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly founder before ſhe gain her Port.</p>
            <p>3. <hi>Treachery</hi> is a Sin that is moſt contrary too to the Intereſt of him in particular who is guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of it; for to none is Treachery more falſe than to the Contrivers of it: witneſs the Fate of <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolom, Achitophel, Zimri, Judas,</hi> and of the <hi>Devil himſelf.</hi> Scarce is there any Inſtance, in Divine,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:63910:6"/> or Prophane Story; but, as you read it in one of the proper Pſalms for this Day, <hi>He that made a Pit and digged it, falls into the Ditch which he made.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 7. 15.</note> And, to follow the Metaphor I juſt now made uſe of, how can he who bores the Hole in the Veſſel hope to eſcape in the common Shipwrack? Or ſhould he otherwiſe provide for the preſent Danger, and get timely to Shore, yet is not <hi>the Hand and Heart of every man againſt ſuch?</hi> For he who is once falſe in his Nature, hath put off his Title to the common Protection due to Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind; hath <hi>out-lawed</hi> himſelf, and is become <hi>Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinum Caput,</hi> the Fox, or Wolf's Head, devoted to common Hatred and Ruine.</p>
            <p>Not to ſay, which is often found upon Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, that he is the mark of his own Venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance; for how frequently doth the Traitor's Heart prove moſt treacherous to it ſelf? how often doth it gall and torment him? And to ſay truth, how is it the concern of <hi>Providence</hi> ſuch ſhould be falſe to themſelves, and not with all their Cunning be able to elude the <hi>Divine Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> whoſe care of Mankind, of the World and its Government, they ſo much defie?</p>
            <p>4 <hi>Treachery</hi> is a Sin (and that one would think ſhould make it not to be ſo over charm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) that is the very <hi>Tranſcript and Copy of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil;</hi> for, <hi>He is a Lyar, and the Father of Lies:</hi> He is
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:63910:6"/> the Arch-Traitor, who began his Treachery in <hi>Heaven,</hi> and is ſtill acting it in all the Deceits and Impoſtures by which he enterprizes on the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wary Sinner: he is in this ſenſe moſt <hi>the Prince of Darkneſs;</hi> and the utmoſt leſſer Traitors can boaſt of all their hidden Plots, is, That they are liſting themſelves <hi>as his Subjects;</hi> and where can that <hi>Villany</hi> end which goes to <hi>Hell</hi> for its <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample</hi> and <hi>Authority?</hi> I ſhall ſcarce need to add, that</p>
            <p>5. <hi>Treachery</hi> is a <hi>Complication</hi> of all other <hi>Sins</hi> and <hi>Miſeries;</hi> which is another Aggravation of the Cheat, that it ſeldom ends where it begins; that the Guilt and Villany increaſe in the acting, and he who at the firſt mention of the <hi>horrid Sin</hi> is apt to ſay with <hi>Hazael, 2 Kings 8. 13. Am I a Dog that I ſhould do this great thing,</hi> is <hi>Dog, Wolf, Bear, Lion,</hi> every thing to which the <hi>Father of Lies</hi> can prompt him, before he hath done.</p>
            <p>'Twould be ſuperfluous to mention the <hi>Baſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> of the Traitor's Mind, how <hi>mean</hi> and <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manly</hi> the Spirit with which he is acted! how apt to ſtoop to any Drudgery to ſave that ſtinking Breath in's Noſtrils which already corrupts the Air he lives in, is the great <hi>Nuſance</hi> and <hi>Peſt</hi> of Humane Society. There's ſomething of Brave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in open Violence; for, 'tis to bid our Enemy ſtand upon's Guard, to bid him look to, and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:63910:7"/> defend himſelf: but, to hide the Weapon where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with we intend to give the Stab, to flatter him to the Face whoſe Ruine we are then deſigning, to <hi>greet,</hi> and at the ſame time <hi>ſmite under the fifth Rib,</hi> to ſay <hi>Hail Maſter,</hi> and <hi>betray,</hi> are the Acts of a <hi>Judas,</hi> or a <hi>Devil</hi> in him.</p>
            <p>This as to our firſt Head; <hi>viz. The heinous nature of Treachery.</hi> Our ſecond is,</p>
            <p>II. To ſhew, what the <hi>Treachery of Iſrael was?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now <hi>that</hi> I doubt not in the beginning of it to limit to their <hi>Revolt from the Houſe of David,</hi> from their <hi>Allegiance</hi> to their <hi>natural Lord</hi> and <hi>he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reditary Sovereign,</hi> and (what can ſcarce be divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded) from their <hi>Loyalty to God himſelf;</hi> for ſo we find it in matter of Fact, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 12. 16. where <hi>Jeroboam</hi> and <hi>his Accomplices</hi> had no ſooner <hi>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered the King, What portion have we in</hi> David? <hi>neither have we Inheritance in the Sons of</hi> Jeſſe, but the next News we have is, <hi>verſ.</hi> 26, 27. their cutting themſelves off from any <hi>Portion in God, from any Inheritance in his eſtabliſh'd Worſhip and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; And</hi> Jeroboam <hi>ſaid in his Heart, Now ſhall the Kingdom return to the Houſe of</hi> David, <hi>if this People go up to do Sacrifice in the Houſe of the Lord at</hi> Jeruſalem: As before, their <hi>Obedience</hi> to their <hi>lawful King,</hi> ſo now, their <hi>Duty to God himſelf</hi> is become a <hi>Grievance; It is too much for you to go up to</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>behold thy Gods, O</hi> Iſrael, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:63910:7"/>
            <p>But was there <hi>nothing</hi> but this <hi>Revolt</hi> that was in the whole time of their continuing to be a People charged upon <hi>Iſrael?</hi> Yes, many are the <hi>particular Guilts</hi> with which the Prophets loade them; <hi>but this</hi> ſeems to be the <hi>Cauſe,</hi> this the <hi>Burden</hi> of all the reſt, that they <hi>walk'd in the ways of</hi> Jeroboam <hi>the Son of</hi> Nebat, <hi>who made</hi> Iſrael <hi>to ſin. This</hi> was the <hi>pulling up the Sluce</hi> that let in all <hi>the Inundation</hi> that afterwards <hi>over-flowed</hi> them, <hi>this</hi> ſo <hi>black a Stain,</hi> that no <hi>length of time,</hi> no <hi>poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of the Crown,</hi> could ever <hi>purge</hi> it; for ſo the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> tells us, <hi>v. 19. That</hi> Iſrael <hi>rebelled againſt the Houſe of</hi> David <hi>to this day:</hi> And the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>in this Sin,</hi> and <hi>the fatal conſequents of it,</hi> was <hi>that</hi> which at laſt made them to be caſt <hi>off by God,</hi> deliver'd into the Hands and Power of the <hi>Aſſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian,</hi> and as to any Account we have of them ever ſince, loſt, from being ſo much as <hi>a People,</hi> in that Captivity; for now, as 'tis <hi>Hoſea</hi> 1. 6. they became <hi>Lo-Ruchama,</hi> and <hi>Lo-ammi, v.</hi> 9. no more either his <hi>beloved</hi> or his <hi>People;</hi> to ſhew them their <hi>Sin</hi> in the <hi>Puniſhment</hi> of it, <hi>they,</hi> who <hi>revolted</hi> from their <hi>lawful Sovereign,</hi> and <hi>their God,</hi> were <hi>to abide many days without a King, without a Prince, and without a Sacrifice, and without an Image, and without an Ephod, and without</hi> Teraphim, <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſea</hi> 3. 4. Without any <hi>eſtabliſh'd Government,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any <hi>the leaſt ſhew,</hi> the very <hi>counterfeit dreſs and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:63910:8"/> ſurface of Religion:</hi> and when to be <hi>reſtored,</hi> it will be <hi>only by returning to their Allegiance to the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity of</hi> David; as it follows <hi>v.</hi> 5. and afterward <hi>ſhall the Children of</hi> Iſrael <hi>return, and ſeek the Lord their God and</hi> David <hi>their King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if <hi>this</hi> be ſo great a <hi>Guilt,</hi> how comes <hi>God</hi> to declare, he doth it upon the occaſion of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoboam</hi>'s taking Arms to reduce the Rebels, and <hi>bring back</hi> the Kingdom again to <hi>Judah,</hi> 1 Kings 12. 21. 24. <hi>that the thing was from him?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer, 'Tis <hi>one thing</hi> for God to <hi>approve,</hi> ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to <hi>permit</hi> any Action. 1. 'Twas <hi>from him,</hi> as thereby the <hi>Houſe of</hi> Solomon was to <hi>be puniſh'd</hi> for <hi>their own Rebellion againſt God,</hi> in <hi>forſaking him, and worſhipping Idols,</hi> 1 Kings 11. 33. 'Twas <hi>from him,</hi> as their not walking in his ways to do that which <hi>was right in his eyes,</hi> had expoſed them to <hi>his juſt Judgments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. 'Twas <hi>from him,</hi> as by his <hi>Providence,</hi> as he had purpos'd to over-rule <hi>their Sin</hi> to his <hi>own Glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3. 'Twas <hi>from him,</hi> and therefore not to be puniſh'd by their Sword, as he would take to himſelf to <hi>repay the Vengeance</hi> that was due to ſo notorious <hi>a Revolt:</hi> as he did by thoſe <hi>many Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verities inflicted on them,</hi> by thoſe many <hi>Changes of the Succeſſion,</hi> no leſs than <hi>nine</hi> or <hi>ten times,</hi> whilſt they continued to be a <hi>Kingdom</hi> and <hi>People,</hi> to ſee
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:63910:8"/> if any <hi>pouring them from Veſſel to Veſſel</hi> would cleanſe them from <hi>their Dregs;</hi> and when that could not be, by giving them up (the greateſt Judgment that can befall any Nation) to that <hi>Anarchy and Confuſion</hi> they ſo much affected.</p>
            <p>But however, 'twas <hi>juſt</hi> in God thus to treat <hi>one</hi> and the <hi>other,</hi> to puniſh <hi>Judah</hi> by <hi>Iſrael's Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion;</hi> this will in no caſe excuſe the <hi>Actors,</hi> no more than it will acquit the <hi>Devil</hi> of his <hi>implaca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Malice,</hi> that whom he ſeduces by his Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, he is likewiſe appointed to be the <hi>unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Inſtrument</hi> ('tis his <hi>Doom</hi> as well as his <hi>Nature) to torment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But might not ſome <hi>great Indignity</hi> put on <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roboam,</hi> ſome very <hi>ſignal Diſobligation</hi> ſtirring up a <hi>Man of publick Spirit,</hi> juſtifie his <hi>utmoſt Reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments?</hi> Might there not be ſome <hi>publick Grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances</hi> that were neceſſary to be <hi>redreſſed?</hi> Or, Might not <hi>Religion</hi> be called in to aſſiſt in ſo <hi>good a Cauſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us ſee then what ſtands upon Record in theſe Matters; for 'tis the <hi>common caſe</hi> of moſt <hi>Traitors,</hi> and was <hi>theirs</hi> who <hi>contrived</hi> and <hi>acted</hi> the black <hi>Tragedy of this day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. As to the <hi>great Indignity</hi> put on <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> the <hi>very ſignal Diſobligations</hi> he had from the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and what moved his <hi>publick Spirit,</hi> you have the Hiſtory, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 11. 26. And <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roboam
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:63910:9"/> the Son of</hi> Nebat, Solomon's <hi>Servant, even He</hi> (that's the Emphaſis the Holy Ghoſt puts on it) <hi>He,</hi> who ſtood in ſo <hi>near a Relation</hi> of <hi>perſonal Duty,</hi> and <hi>ſtricter Attendance</hi> to his Maſter, who was of <hi>his conſtant and daily Guard</hi> (as every Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſtick to a Prince is) <hi>even he lift up his hand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the King. And this was the Cauſe that he lift up his hand againſt the King;</hi> Solomon <hi>built</hi> Millo, <hi>and repaired the Breaches of the City of</hi> David <hi>his Father;</hi> 'twas a <hi>Diſtaſte</hi> taken at the <hi>Strength</hi> and <hi>Security of his Prince,</hi> the <hi>Envy</hi> he had at his <hi>Greatneſs</hi> and <hi>Power;</hi> for we find very little <hi>Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion</hi> or <hi>Injuſtice</hi> charged on <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Reign. <hi>Indignities</hi> and <hi>Diſobligations</hi> he had received none from <hi>Solomon,</hi> till he ſtood in <hi>open Defiance</hi> and <hi>Rebellion.</hi> All that <hi>Solomon</hi> was faulty herein, was, his advancing <hi>Jeroboam</hi> to that <hi>Dignity,</hi> whereby he began now to think himſelf a <hi>Match for his Prince, v.</hi> 28. He had made <hi>him Ruler over all the Charge of the Houſe of</hi> Joſeph: ſo <hi>dangerous</hi> is it to raiſe men of <hi>turbulent</hi> and <hi>ambitious Minds,</hi> that like <hi>Lucifer,</hi> preſently <hi>Aſcendam, &amp; ero ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis altiſſimo, I will aſcend, and be like the moſt high,</hi> is what comes next into their Thoughts; Their <hi>Heighth</hi> makes them <hi>giddy,</hi> and every thing <hi>turns round about</hi> with them; their <hi>Glory</hi> only fits them, ('tis the Pattern the <hi>Son of the Morning</hi> hath left his Followers) to be <hi>greater Devils.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:63910:9"/>2. As to the <hi>publick Grievances</hi> neceſſary to be redreſſed, (for 'tis pity there ſhould not be ſome <hi>colour</hi> for ſo <hi>brave an Attempt</hi>) what <hi>were they?</hi> We muſt again conſult the Hiſtory, as 'tis rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 12. 4. and the whole Complaint ſumm'd up in that <hi>grievous Yoke Solomon</hi> had put upon them; and <hi>what that</hi> was, you have at large 1 <hi>Kings 4. 7. &amp;c.</hi> 'Twas only the more <hi>regular ordering</hi> of his <hi>Kingdom</hi> and <hi>Family;</hi> 'twas his <hi>ſettling his Dominion abroad,</hi> and <hi>ſecuring</hi> to them <hi>Peace and Plenty</hi> at home; 'twas his making <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah and Iſrael to dwell ſafely, every man under his Vine and under his Fig-tree, from</hi> Dan <hi>even to</hi> Beer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheba, <hi>v.</hi> 24. 25. Their <hi>great Grievance</hi> was, That the <hi>Wiſdom of God was with him, ch. 3. v.</hi> 28. that according to <hi>that</hi> Wiſdom he framed thoſe ſteddy <hi>Rules of Policy,</hi> which the Sons of <hi>Belial,</hi> who were for caſting <hi>off every Yoke,</hi> whoſe diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Lives could bear no <hi>Reſtraint,</hi> could not withſtand.</p>
            <p>And how <hi>clamorous</hi> and <hi>noiſy</hi> are they preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in their Complaints, how <hi>diligent</hi> to find a <hi>fit Perſon</hi> to head the <hi>Faction?</hi> and who ſo fit as a <hi>diſcontented Courtier, a diſobliged Favourite; Jerobo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am</hi> muſt be <hi>called home from Egypt, 1 Kings 12. v.</hi> 3. A <hi>Fugitive</hi> preſently <hi>adopted</hi> into a Patriot, and none ſo <hi>proper</hi> to aſſert the <hi>Rights and Liberties of the People,</hi> as one, who by his <hi>Rebellion</hi> had forfeited
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:63910:10"/> all <hi>his own.</hi> Theſe are <hi>their intolerable Grievances,</hi> and not to be redreſſed, but by deſtroying <hi>Root and Branch; Rehoboam</hi> is the preſent <hi>Oppreſſor,</hi> his Father <hi>Solomon</hi> made the <hi>Yoke,</hi> and <hi>David</hi>'s Name too muſt be brought in to encreaſe the <hi>Odium; v. 16. What Portion have we in</hi> David? <hi>neither have we Inheritance in the Son of</hi> Jeſſe: <hi>What good</hi> did we ever receive from any <hi>of the Line?</hi> No, <hi>the Succeſſion muſt be alter'd,</hi> we'll <hi>chooſe</hi> our own Prince; <hi>Jeroboam</hi> is our <hi>Man: Solomon</hi> was cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and would have <hi>bribed</hi> him by <hi>high Offices</hi> to have been of's Party, but the <hi>Temptation</hi> was in vain; he was of a more <hi>publick Spirit,</hi> a tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er <hi>Patriot,</hi> and more <hi>a Lover of his Countury,</hi> than thus to be <hi>taken off.</hi> He ſhall be <hi>or Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral,</hi> he <hi>our Protector,</hi> to <hi>thy Tents, O</hi> Iſrael!</p>
            <p>From which, put together, 'tis obvious to note,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That 'tis not the <hi>Wiſdom</hi> of the Prince, the <hi>Juſtice,</hi> or <hi>Proſperity</hi> of his Reign; not the <hi>emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Piety</hi> and <hi>extraordinary Virtues</hi> of thoſe who ſit on the Throne, can exempt them from being malign'd by <hi>Factious, Seditious,</hi> and <hi>Ambitious Spirits;</hi> for then <hi>Solomon</hi> and <hi>David</hi> would have been free from ſuch Reflections; or, what is infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely above any of theſe Compariſons, then would <hi>Heaven,</hi> the <hi>Kingdom of God,</hi> and the <hi>Seat of his</hi> Glory, have been ſecured from <hi>Treaſon.</hi> But if the <hi>Throne</hi> of the <hi>wiſeſt</hi> and <hi>beſt Princes,</hi> if the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:63910:10"/> 
               <hi>Throne of God</hi> himſelf be not <hi>free from Conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies,</hi> as indeed the more <hi>Happineſs,</hi> the more <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Proſperity,</hi> the more <hi>Holineſs</hi> any <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> enjoys, the more likely is it to be the <hi>Mark</hi> and <hi>Prey</hi> of the <hi>Traitor,</hi> the more malign'd and oppoſed by the <hi>Devil</hi> and his <hi>Inſtruments,</hi> This may ſerve to leſſen our Admiration, though at the ſame time it ought to heighten the Grief and Repentance <hi>of this Day,</hi> that both a <hi>Solomon</hi> and a <hi>David</hi> fell in ſo <hi>wiſe,</hi> ſo <hi>proſperous,</hi> (for what was not the Nation bleſſed with under his Reign, before thoſe unhappy times) ſo <hi>religious</hi> a Prince. As alſo,</p>
            <p n="2">2. From hence we may note, how impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble 'tis to oblige a Rebel to his <hi>Duty.</hi> But why ſhould we admire, that <hi>Preferment</hi> could not retain <hi>Jeroboam</hi> in his Allegiance, when the <hi>high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt place</hi> in the <hi>Court of Heaven</hi> could not retain <hi>Lucifer (that Spirit who worketh in the Children of Diſobedience,</hi> Epheſ. 2. 2.) in <hi>his.</hi> But I proceed to the third Enquiry in this matter; <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Whether Religion in any ſort might not be called in to aſſiſt in ſo good a Cauſe?</hi> 'Twas the Courſe <hi>Jeroboam</hi> here took, and is the <hi>uſual practice</hi> of the <hi>Rebel;</hi> and but requiſite to ſuch Deſigns it ſhould be ſo, there being <hi>nothing</hi> that hath a more <hi>powerful Influence</hi> on the Minds of men, than the being perſwaded, that <hi>he</hi> who is <hi>King of Kings,</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:63910:11"/> and <hi>Lord of Lords,</hi> whoſe <hi>Prerogative 'tis to ſet up one and pull down another,</hi> hath his hand in the Revolution: To this purpoſe, <hi>Divine Authority</hi> ſhall be urged for the Change: There goes a Prophecy of <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> that <hi>he</hi> ſhould Reign, 1 <hi>Kings 11. 13. &amp;c.</hi> and what ſhould he do but haſten the <hi>fulfilling</hi> of it? <hi>Who</hi> would not obey <hi>a Revelation</hi> in <hi>ſuch a Caſe?</hi> Who would not concur with <hi>Providence</hi> to put the <hi>Crown</hi> on <hi>his own head?</hi> Or is not the <hi>reforming of Religion,</hi> ('tis that <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> good Man, chiefly aims at) the ſuiting it to the Nature of that <hi>Infinite Being</hi> we adore, in appointing him <hi>publick Worſhip</hi> at <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thel, a juſt Plea?</hi> Behold the <hi>Heaven and the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of Heavens cannot contain him,</hi> how much leſs <hi>any houſe</hi> Man can build? What is the <hi>Glory</hi> and <hi>Magnificence</hi> of the <hi>Temple at Jeruſalem,</hi> to his <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſe Majeſty?</hi> What the <hi>holineſs of any particular place,</hi> to <hi>him</hi> who is <hi>every where?</hi> Why muſt we <hi>confine the Deity, or reſtrain his Preſence and Bleſſing</hi> to <hi>one City,</hi> whoſe <hi>Goodneſs</hi> is <hi>over all his Works?</hi> Is it not <hi>his Temple</hi> wherever a <hi>pious Soul inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits? his Reſidence</hi> wherever his <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Power</hi> ſhew themſelves? Why is <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> better than <hi>Shechem?</hi> Why <hi>Zion</hi> (are not all parts of the World alike his Workmanſhip?) better than <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel?</hi> Why muſt <hi>we go up to</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>to Worſhip,</hi> who can reach <hi>heaven</hi> any where with
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:63910:11"/> a <hi>devout Prayer?</hi> Come, 'tis not the <hi>Place,</hi> but the <hi>Sacrifice;</hi> not the <hi>Temple,</hi> but the <hi>Offering</hi> God reſpects, not <hi>a long and tedious travelling with the Feet,</hi> but <hi>the quick and frequent Aſcent</hi> of the <hi>Heart he</hi> accepts. To tye all Holineſs to the <hi>Cathedral of Jeruſalem,</hi> is but a <hi>Trick of the houſe of</hi> David, a <hi>Politick Fetch</hi> of <hi>Solomon</hi> and <hi>his abuſed Wiſdom,</hi> to <hi>continue the Succeſſion in his Line,</hi> whatever the <hi>Perſon</hi> be, how great an <hi>Enemy ſoever</hi> to his <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,</hi> to our <hi>Property,</hi> and <hi>true Religion;</hi> 'tis but to ſtrengthen an <hi>Oppreſſive Kingdom,</hi> inſtead of <hi>Whips</hi> (tis what <hi>Rehoboam</hi> bid us expect) <hi>to chaſtiſe us with Scorpions:</hi> We have had too much already of the <hi>Father's Loins,</hi> to venture the Tryal of the <hi>Son's Little-finger, 1 Kings</hi> 12. 10. No, <hi>this</hi> is a <hi>Yoke</hi> is <hi>intolerable</hi> to be borne by <hi>free-born</hi> Men, <hi>thoſe</hi> whom <hi>God</hi> owns for his <hi>peculiar People:</hi> What! to be denied the <hi>Liberty of our Religion?</hi> to have <hi>our Conſciences fettered?</hi> not to <hi>ſerve God</hi> in any place? to have <hi>Jehovah,</hi> another piece of <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Cunning, to be no where ſo much as mention'd, but <hi>where</hi> they pleaſe? <hi>Thus to limit the holy One of Iſrael,</hi> who can endure it? What honeſt-hearted Child of <hi>Abraham? Brave, Faithful, Comprehending, Abraham,</hi> who ſet up an Altar wherever he came, can ſubmit to the Tyranny? <hi>Jacob,</hi> I am ſure, thought not ſo ill of <hi>Bethel, Geneſ.</hi> 28. 19. as theſe <hi>high-flown, ceremonial Church-men</hi> do: The <hi>Promiſe
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:63910:12"/> of the Bleſſing is to all Nations,</hi> and why then muſt we be thus unreaſonably reſtrained <hi>to one</hi> pitiful Spot of Ground? <hi>No,</hi> We have been <hi>too long</hi> fool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with theſe <hi>Shams</hi> and <hi>Fopperies; David</hi> would fain have been at it, in <hi>building a houſe</hi> too, had not <hi>God forbid</hi> him; <hi>Solomon,</hi> the craftier of the <hi>two,</hi> made a ſhift, by the <hi>Strength of his Navy,</hi> (come, 'twas nothing elſe but his <hi>prosperous Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racies</hi>) to heap up a little more Wealth than his Neighbours, by his <hi>wheadling</hi> and <hi>drawing</hi> in other leſs wary Princes to aſſiſt in the Work, to ſet <hi>up the Idol:</hi> but, <hi>God</hi> be thank'd, we are better in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed <hi>now</hi> in the <hi>Reaſon of Religion,</hi> and have <hi>Strength, and hands as well as hearts,</hi> to defend it; We know our <hi>God is a Spirit,</hi> and as <hi>ſuch</hi> he hath ſo often appeared for us, and <hi>as ſuch</hi> we <hi>will Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> him. Far be it from <hi>us</hi> who have been for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly reſcued from <hi>Slavery</hi> by ſo <hi>many Miracles,</hi> to run into <hi>it</hi> again; We have a <hi>brave</hi> and <hi>worthy Patriot</hi> to be our <hi>Captain; Jeroboam,</hi> whom <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> himſelf durſt not but prefer, <hi>he</hi> well under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood the Eminency of his <hi>Parts</hi> and <hi>Valour,</hi> and could not even then <hi>ſuppreſs</hi> his <hi>growing Merits.</hi> 'Tis a Providence, and we ought to lay hold on it, that we have ſo <hi>gallant,</hi> ſo <hi>conſcientious a Leader,</hi> who hath ſo true a Value for our <hi>Rights</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> to <hi>thy Tents,</hi> ('tis a <hi>juſt</hi> and <hi>noble Cauſe,</hi> the <hi>Cauſe of God</hi> and <hi>his People) to thy Arms
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:63910:12"/> O Iſrael.</hi> For thus may we ſuppoſe ſome bold <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious, blaſphemous Ringleader,</hi> ſome <hi>Plebeian</hi> Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor then inflaming the <hi>Mobile;</hi> 'tis the method Incendiaries uſually take to make <hi>Religion</hi> ſerve the <hi>Cheat;</hi> 'twas the <hi>Artifice</hi> of our <hi>Modern Saints;</hi> and how far 'tis apt to prevail on thoſe who cannot diſtinguiſh between <hi>Noiſe</hi> and <hi>Reaſon, Zeal</hi> and <hi>Rage,</hi> the <hi>curſed Villany</hi> of <hi>this day</hi> doth but too plainly declare.</p>
            <p>But to ſee then whither there be any weight in this ſort of arguing; and,</p>
            <p n="1">1. As to the <hi>Prophecy</hi> that went of <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> that <hi>he</hi> ſhould Reign; (I the more willingly take notice of this, becauſe too we have had our <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation-men,</hi> thoſe who never wanted a <hi>Viſion,</hi> a <hi>Prediction,</hi> an <hi>Euthuſiaſm,</hi> to colour the Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) If <hi>God's fore-ſeeing</hi> and <hi>predicting</hi> any Event muſt <hi>juſtifie it,</hi> what <hi>Action</hi> is there, ever ſo <hi>hei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous,</hi> what <hi>Crime,</hi> ever ſo <hi>vile,</hi> will be left <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtified?</hi> Doth his <hi>Omniſcience,</hi> who ſees what is <hi>future</hi> as if <hi>preſent, purge the Guilt?</hi> then would the <hi>oppreſſing of the</hi> Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> by the <hi>Egy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptians, the Murders of</hi> Hazael, <hi>the Madneſs of</hi> Jehu, the <hi>Treaſon of</hi> Judas, <hi>the coming of</hi> Antichriſt <hi>and falſe Prophets, of the Man of Sin,</hi> and <hi>Son of Perdition,</hi> 2 Theſ. 2, 3. be all <hi>hallowed</hi> by the <hi>Oracle.</hi> For <hi>what</hi> is there of <hi>theſe</hi> or any other <hi>Villanies,</hi> that comes not within the <hi>compaſs of his Knowledge?</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:63910:13"/> But to aſſert <hi>them</hi> therefore to be the <hi>Effects of his Will</hi> and <hi>good Pleaſure,</hi> to be <hi>what</hi> he <hi>approves</hi> and <hi>allows,</hi> (which is what <hi>thoſe</hi> would inſinuate who make uſe of this Argument) is to forget, that <hi>he</hi> hath as well <hi>predicted</hi> a <hi>Day of Judgment</hi> wherein to <hi>arraign,</hi> and a <hi>Hell to puniſh ſuch Offenders.</hi> There's a vaſt Difference between <hi>foretelling</hi> an Event, either <hi>good</hi> or <hi>bad,</hi> that <hi>ſhall</hi> be; and <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealing</hi> or <hi>commanding a Duty</hi> that <hi>ought to be</hi> done. <hi>God</hi> never intended a <hi>Prophecy,</hi> as <hi>ſuch,</hi> to be a <hi>Rule;</hi> nor will it any more abſolve the <hi>Traitor</hi> that his <hi>Wickedneſs is foretold,</hi> than 'twill thoſe of whom the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſpeaks, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. 11, 12. to <hi>whom God ſends ſtrong Deluſions</hi> (they <hi>whoſe</hi> caſe it is would do well to conſider, what ſhould be the <hi>cauſe</hi> of ſo <hi>heavy a Judgment</hi> on them) <hi>that they ſhould believe a Lye, that they might be damned.</hi> This as to the <hi>Prophecy</hi> of <hi>Jeroboam's Reigning,</hi> and the <hi>Inſufficiency of arguing</hi> any <hi>Right</hi> from thence: 'Twas the <hi>Caſe of David</hi> before him, but ſo, that he ſtayed <hi>God's time</hi> for the <hi>fulfilling of it;</hi> left it to <hi>him</hi> who foretold it, to take his <hi>own method,</hi> and uſe his <hi>own means,</hi> to <hi>verifie the Prediction.</hi> Let us ſee, whether</p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>Pretence of Religion</hi> in any ſort, or the <hi>new modelling thereof</hi> (it ſhall be called <hi>reforming</hi> by the <hi>Uſurper) to ſerve the Revolt,</hi> be any <hi>better Plea?</hi> There's no doubt, as I before obſerved,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:63910:13"/> but the <hi>Name of Religion</hi> is a very <hi>powerful per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſive:</hi> the <hi>bringing God</hi> into the <hi>Party</hi> is what muſt beget an <hi>Awe</hi> and <hi>Reverence</hi> for whatever ſhall be acted. But why ſhould <hi>a Jew</hi> (for I would confine my ſelf to the <hi>merits</hi> of the Cauſe before us) be impoſed upon to think that <hi>God,</hi> who hath given his own <hi>Name</hi> and <hi>Authority</hi> to <hi>Princes (Exodus 22. 28. Thou ſhalt not revile the Gods) who</hi> hath not only required that the <hi>outward Actions</hi> of the Subject, their <hi>Words</hi> and <hi>Language,</hi> be <hi>dutiful;</hi> but (as if he would ſhare with them his own <hi>Prerogative</hi> of taking <hi>Cognizance</hi> of the <hi>Heart</hi> and its <hi>Motions</hi>) that they pay them the <hi>Reverence</hi> of their <hi>very Thoughts,</hi> (for ſo it runs, <hi>Eccleſ. 10. 20. Curſe not the King, no not in thy Thought.) That God, who</hi> hath entailed ſo great <hi>Temporal Bleſſings</hi> on the <hi>Obedience</hi> paid to <hi>him,</hi> ('tis by all agreed to be one meaning of the <hi>Fifth Commandment,) who</hi> hath ſo immediately intruſted them with the <hi>Care of his Laws</hi> and <hi>Worſhip,</hi> hath ſo well <hi>qualified them</hi> for the <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charging</hi> that great <hi>Truſt,</hi> who gave <hi>Wiſdom</hi> to <hi>Solomon, Piety</hi> and <hi>Courage</hi> to <hi>David,</hi> promiſed his <hi>Preſence</hi> and <hi>Bleſſing</hi> to <hi>them all, (2 Sam. 14, 15, &amp;c.</hi> 29.) made their <hi>Perſons</hi> ſacred, and <hi>anointed them</hi> for his <hi>own?</hi> Why, I ſay, ſhould a <hi>Jew</hi> be impoſed upon to think, That <hi>God, who</hi> hath ſo far joyn'd his own <hi>Intereſt, Honour,</hi> and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:63910:14"/> 
               <hi>Authority,</hi> with that of his <hi>Vicegerents,</hi> ſo far im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed his own <hi>Sovereignty</hi> and <hi>Character</hi> upon them, ſhould ſo forget all this, as to <hi>conſpire</hi> with any <hi>Uſurper</hi> againſt <hi>them?</hi> ſhould encourage or approve the <hi>Revolt,</hi> which, as 'tis declared in the Caſe of <hi>Corah and his Accomplices riſing</hi> up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Moſes and Aaron,</hi> is no other, than <hi>gathering together</hi> againſt <hi>himſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as the <hi>preſent Religion</hi> of the <hi>Jew,</hi> how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever by the <hi>Mutinous</hi> falſly gloſſed upon, could be <hi>no Plea,</hi> ſo much leſs ought any <hi>new Model</hi> thereof (<hi>Reforming</hi> as the <hi>Uſurper</hi> will ſtile it) be contrived to <hi>ſerve the Revolt:</hi> for what though <hi>God be every where,</hi> muſt he not therefore have any <hi>Place ſet apart</hi> for his more <hi>ſolemn Worſhip?</hi> Or is not the appointing it at <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel</hi> (were that the true ſtate of the Queſtion) as much a <hi>limiting the Holy One of Iſrael,</hi> as 'twas at <hi>Jeruſalem?</hi> If there muſt be no <hi>diſtinction</hi> of Place in his <hi>Service</hi> becauſe he fills <hi>all places</hi> by his <hi>Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence,</hi> why don't they as well level <hi>Heaven and Earth,</hi> and make his <hi>Throne</hi> and his <hi>Foot-ſtool</hi> the ſame? Or is it not at the <hi>Choice of God himſelf,</hi> to put his <hi>Name, promiſe his Preſence,</hi> and manifeſt <hi>his Glory,</hi> more in <hi>one Place</hi> than another? Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, 'tis not to <hi>limit</hi> himſelf, who is <hi>immenſe</hi> and <hi>infinite,</hi> but his <hi>Worſhippers;</hi> 'tis to ſecure a <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick and certain Homage</hi> from <hi>them</hi> in <hi>ſome place,</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:63910:14"/> who if left to themſelves, would be apt to pay it in none. I meddle not with the <hi>Typical</hi> and <hi>Myſtical</hi> Reaſons, why <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> is preferred be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all other <hi>Places,</hi> but only frame the Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction for the <hi>mutinous Jew,</hi> as it might likewiſe ſuit the <hi>Pretences of our Reformers,</hi> who upon <hi>juſt as good Grounds</hi> ſet up their <hi>ſeparate Meetings, their ſeditious Conventicles</hi> and Congregations, as <hi>Jero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam</hi> did his <hi>Calves</hi> at <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel,</hi> in Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to the eſtabliſh'd <hi>Order</hi> and <hi>Decency</hi> of our Church, till <hi>they</hi> diſturbed <hi>the Peace</hi> of it, (for that's the import of <hi>its Name</hi>) of <hi>our Jeruſalem.</hi> Which, to ſum up the Argument <hi>for both,</hi> is no more than this, (and let it be ſpoken to the <hi>Confuſion of their Cauſe) That</hi> what the <hi>Rebel</hi> at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts, is not to be juſtified, but by <hi>corrupting</hi> the <hi>Religion</hi> he pretends <hi>for it,</hi> by <hi>debauching</hi> its <hi>Principles</hi> and <hi>renouncing</hi> its <hi>Precepts;</hi> that <hi>only Schiſm</hi> and <hi>Idolatry</hi> are <hi>proper Advocates</hi> for <hi>Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion:</hi> and, to ſpeak truly, 'tis the <hi>ſame Anarchy in the Church</hi> that brings in <hi>Schiſm</hi> and <hi>Idolatry</hi> there, (for <hi>Idolatry,</hi> the ſetting up <hi>more</hi> or <hi>other Gods</hi> is a <hi>Commonwealth</hi> and <hi>Populacy</hi> in <hi>Religion</hi>) as 'tis, that brings in <hi>Faction</hi> and <hi>Sedition</hi> in the State: <hi>Both</hi> are from <hi>Republican,</hi> i. e. <hi>Atheiſtical Principles:</hi> And 'tis no wonder, (let them take to themſelves for once the <hi>Honour of their free Philoſophy</hi>) 'tis no wonder, I ſay, that <hi>Commonwealths</hi> are obſerv'd
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:63910:15"/> equally to cheriſh <hi>all Religions; i. e.</hi> to govern (whatever they talk to the Prejudice of <hi>Monarchy</hi>) to extort from, and oppreſs their <hi>Subjects,</hi> rather their <hi>Slaves</hi> and <hi>Vaſſals,</hi> as if they believed <hi>none.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have ſaid what I intended concerning <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el's Treachery,</hi> with the <hi>Remarks</hi> thereon I thought neceſſary to the <hi>preſent Subject</hi> we are on:</p>
            <p>III. How her <hi>Siſter Judah</hi> exceeded her in her <hi>Guilt,</hi> comes now to be <hi>ſpoken</hi> to: <hi>Which</hi> I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend not to apply to the ſame <hi>Guilt in Specie;</hi> for <hi>Judah</hi> had not <hi>revolted</hi> from their <hi>Allegiance to their Prince,</hi> but what was of a much higher nature, from their <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Allegiance to their God;</hi> and on that account their <hi>ſin</hi> was the greater, as 'twould have been had their <hi>Crimes</hi> been other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe <hi>the ſame,</hi> the <hi>Guilt of Judah</hi> would have been the more notorious of the two: becauſe, as I before touched it, heighten'd by theſe following Aggravations: <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. That what <hi>Judah</hi> did, was under the <hi>Covert of the true Religion;</hi> 'Twas againſt the <hi>cleareſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation</hi> of their Duty, the moſt <hi>ſenſible Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations</hi> of the <hi>Divine Power</hi> and <hi>Goodneſs,</hi> the <hi>Preſence</hi> of <hi>God himſelf</hi> with, and his peculiar <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence</hi> ſtill preſiding over them; in a word, againſt thoſe <hi>great</hi> and <hi>diſtinguiſhing Priviledges</hi> which no other <hi>part of Mankind</hi> could pretend to.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:63910:15"/>2. That <hi>what Judah</hi> did, was not only againſt ſo <hi>great Mercies,</hi> but againſt as <hi>great Judgments</hi> too; thoſe <hi>manifeſt Warnings</hi> of that <hi>good Providence,</hi> I mean, which had ſo tenderly dealt with <hi>her,</hi> as to make her <hi>Siſter Iſrael</hi> the ſad Example of <hi>that Vengeance,</hi> he would thereby have deterred <hi>her</hi> from; 'tis the <hi>Argument</hi> of the Context, and the Emphaſis of the Text, <hi>yet her treacherous Siſter</hi> Judah <hi>feared not.</hi> And for the <hi>true Religion</hi> to proſtitute it ſelf to that <hi>Sin</hi> it ſo expreſly <hi>prohibits,</hi> for <hi>thoſe</hi> who could not be <hi>ignorant</hi> of their <hi>Duty</hi> to make their <hi>extraordinary Knowledge</hi> only ſerve to inſtruct them in <hi>greater Impiety; thoſe</hi> who could not but be <hi>ſenſible</hi> of the <hi>ſingular Favours of Heaven</hi> towards them, to improve <hi>all</hi> to the <hi>diſhonour</hi> of their <hi>great Benefactor,</hi> and <hi>turn his Grace into Wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonneſs.</hi> For <hi>thoſe</hi> who had before their Eyes ſuch a <hi>Spectacle</hi> of what <hi>their Sin</hi> muſt end in, if not forſaken and amended, as <hi>that</hi> of <hi>forlorn rejected Iſrael;</hi> for them to make the <hi>Law,</hi> to adminiſter to <hi>their Guilt,</hi> the <hi>Promiſes or Threats</hi> therein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd to <hi>promote their Impiety,</hi> ſuch <hi>ſignal and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous,</hi> whether <hi>Mercies</hi> or <hi>Judgments,</hi> only drudge to <hi>Sin</hi> and <hi>Hell,</hi> that's the <hi>Aggravation,</hi> that's the <hi>Horror.</hi> And now I come with reference to what is the <hi>Subject of this Days Lamentation,</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:63910:16"/>
            <p>IV. To draw the Parallel in our own Caſe; for <hi>we</hi> have <hi>our Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Judah</hi> too; give me leave ſo to expreſs it, thoſe, on the one hand of a <hi>corrupt</hi> and <hi>ſuperſtitious,</hi> and <hi>on the other,</hi> as they give themſelves the Stile, of the <hi>true Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant</hi> and <hi>beſt reformed Religion,</hi> both deeply con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd in the <hi>heinous Guilt of Treachery,</hi> and that, as I ſhewed it in the <hi>Caſe of Jeroboam</hi> and <hi>his Complot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> as it extends to a <hi>joint Revolt</hi> from <hi>God</hi> and <hi>the King,</hi> to the <hi>undermining the Government</hi> in <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State,</hi> both <hi>highly guilty</hi> in this matter, but <hi>the latter</hi> the more <hi>inexcuſable of the two.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to the <hi>Guilt</hi> of the <hi>former, i. e.</hi> of the <hi>Church of Rome, whom</hi> in the Parallel I here call <hi>Iſrael,</hi> will not their uſurped <hi>Primacy,</hi> ſo contrary to the Doctrine of Chriſt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 20. 25. and afterwards their pretended <hi>Infallibility,</hi> the only <hi>Prerogative</hi> of <hi>Heaven's Crown,</hi> taken in to juſtifie that and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very other Uſurpation whatever, too nearly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble the <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> of <hi>Iſrael?</hi> And what have <hi>theſe Calves</hi> of <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel,</hi> (to follow the Alluſion) ever ſince <hi>bleated</hi> out, but the <hi>Excommunicating, Depoſing,</hi> and <hi>Extirpating of Princes,</hi> and <hi>Hell</hi> and <hi>Damnation</hi> to all who would not joyn with them in the <hi>Holy Cheat.</hi> The ill Conſequences where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, have been felt no where more than in <hi>theſe Kingdoms</hi> whereof <hi>we</hi> are; witneſs the <hi>Slavery</hi> in
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:63910:16"/> which <hi>Prince and People,</hi> for ſo <hi>many Ages together,</hi> were held <hi>by it;</hi> and when the <hi>Yoke</hi> was caſt off, What <hi>Plots, Conſpiracies,</hi> and <hi>Treaſons,</hi> were ſtill hatching by <hi>thoſe of that Communion?</hi> So <hi>notorious,</hi> ſo <hi>hateful</hi> were their <hi>Practices,</hi> till at length what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever <hi>Miſchief</hi> befell the Nation, was ſuſpected to ariſe <hi>from thence:</hi> So <hi>general</hi> was the <hi>Odium of that Name,</hi> that like a <hi>common Thief,</hi> every Felony, by whomſoever committed, is charged upon <hi>them:</hi> and it hath been the <hi>common Craft of every</hi> Party almoſt, to raiſe the <hi>Suſpicion upon the Papiſt,</hi> and ſend the <hi>Hue</hi> and <hi>Cry</hi> after them, that ſo them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves might paſs <hi>unapprehended,</hi> and <hi>wholly fly from Juſtice.</hi> How far they had a ſhare in <hi>contriving</hi> or <hi>acting</hi> the <hi>Tragedy of this Day,</hi> (for that too hath been charged upon them) <hi>God</hi> who knows the Secrets of all Hearts, can beſt tell; and there will be <hi>a day of Revelation of all things:</hi> How far in <hi>l ae r Conſpiracies,</hi> they would do well to look to, who pretend ſo much to <hi>abhor and deteſt their Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions.</hi> For this I cannot but on this Occaſion take notice of, That</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>The Jeſuits,</hi> thoſe great <hi>Plotters of that Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and <hi>private Presbyteries,</hi> came firſt into <hi>England</hi> about the ſame time.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That they <hi>both</hi> behaved themſelves, in their <hi>ſeveral</hi> (if <hi>ſeveral</hi>) Deſigns by the <hi>ſame Model;</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:63910:17"/> the <hi>one in indicting Councils, ſummoning Synods, enact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and reverſing Orders, and exerciſing of all manner of Papal Juriſdiction; the other, in appointing Meetings both Claſſical</hi> and <hi>Synodical,</hi> in <hi>ſetting down Decrees, in reverſing Orders, in electing Miniſters, exacting Subſcriptions, executing Cenſures of Suſpenſion</hi> and <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication, where they thought good,</hi> writing ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly by the <hi>ſame Copy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. That the <hi>Principles</hi> on which they proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to <hi>theſe Enormities,</hi> were, and are ſtill the <hi>ſame.</hi> What thoſe of the <hi>Romiſh Communion</hi> do by vertue of the <hi>Power</hi> pretended to be lodged <hi>in the Church,</hi> and <hi>abſolute Juriſdiction, Chriſt,</hi> as they would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade their Diſciples, hath given to his <hi>Vicar</hi> over <hi>all the World;</hi> That the <hi>Brethren</hi> (for ſo they ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led themſelves) <hi>arrogating</hi> to their <hi>Presbyteries,</hi> as they are the <hi>chief Miniſters of the Kingdom of Chriſt, are to uphold his Throne,</hi> to weild <hi>God's Scepter,</hi> and manage his <hi>holy Yoke</hi> (for ſo they phraſe it) which is <hi>their Diſcipline.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. That if the <hi>Motto</hi> of the one be (ſo ſome tell us the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> is) <hi>Woe to Princes,</hi> the <hi>Republican Humour</hi> and <hi>rebellious Attempts</hi> of the <hi>other</hi> may ſerve for a <hi>Comment</hi> on it. I ſhall give but one In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of this thorough Accord of <hi>theſe Brethren in Iniquity,</hi> and 'tis a very eminent one: 'tis what I find in <hi>two ſeveral Authors</hi> about <hi>the ſame time,</hi> when
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:63910:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>theſe Innovations</hi> were bringing in among us, the one <hi>a Calviniſt,</hi> the other a <hi>Romaniſt,</hi> both pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing their Books,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Under <hi>the ſame Title, De jure Magiſtratuum in ſubditos, &amp; Officio ſubditorum erga Magiſtratus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Uſing the ſame Arguments, &amp; mutatis mutan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis,</hi> the very ſame words, only ſuch <hi>Alterations</hi> made as might ſerve their <hi>ſeveral Hypotheſes;</hi> and</p>
            <p n="3">3. Concluding in the <hi>lawfulneſs</hi> of <hi>reſiſting, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing,</hi> and <hi>extirpating Supreme Powers.</hi> The ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Authors are <hi>Johannes Baptiſta Ficklerus</hi> of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Perſwaſion, and an <hi>Anonymous Diſciple</hi> of <hi>John Calvin;</hi> and the later of the two hath the Honour to be firſt on the Argument: Their Books were publiſh'd between the Years of 1576 and 1578, both within the time of <hi>Buchanan's Writing</hi> and <hi>Publiſhing</hi> his <hi>De jure Regni apud Scotos;</hi> all which, <hi>i. e.</hi> the firſt coming of <hi>the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits</hi> into <hi>England,</hi> the ſettling of <hi>private Presbyteries</hi> by the <hi>Brethren,</hi> and the writing of theſe <hi>ſeveral Books, one</hi> in <hi>France, another</hi> in <hi>Germany,</hi> a third in <hi>Scotland,</hi> to which I might add the many <hi>moſt viru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Pamphlets</hi> then ſent abroad at home, ſuch as <hi>Goodman, True Obedience, Martin Mar-prelate, the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration of the Diſcipline</hi> ſet out by <hi>Penry</hi> and <hi>Udal, Miniſters,</hi> by <hi>Job Throckmorton, Knightly, Wig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſton, Laicks,</hi> in 1588. the <hi>ſame Year</hi> when the <hi>Queen</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:63910:18"/> was depoſed by <hi>Sixtus Quintus</hi> his <hi>Bull,</hi> and the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Spain</hi> came with his <hi>Armado</hi> to <hi>ſeize</hi> the <hi>forfeited Crown:</hi> and all this juſt about the time when <hi>Subſcription</hi> was in <hi>England</hi> firſt required to <hi>the Book of Articles,</hi> ſo much the dread of all <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vators</hi> both in <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State,</hi> becauſe ſo much for the <hi>Stability</hi> of both; <hi>Ab uno diſce omnes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, becauſe how near <hi>Brethren</hi> ſoever they are <hi>in Iniquity,</hi> yet there <hi>is nothing</hi> in <hi>which they</hi> are ſo <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſie</hi> as to be thought <hi>ſuch;</hi> let us a little more di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly ſee what the <hi>Guilt</hi> of the <hi>one</hi> is in <hi>this Affair,</hi> and how the <hi>others</hi> is <hi>aggravated</hi> beyond it.</p>
            <p>'Tis <hi>Guilt,</hi> very <hi>enormous Guilt,</hi> to be <hi>thoſe,</hi> who like <hi>Jeroboam the Son of Nebat</hi> make <hi>Iſrael to ſin,</hi> who corrupt and adulterate the <hi>Principles</hi> of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. <hi>This,</hi> in the firſt Inſtance of it, certainly <hi>is a Guilt</hi> of the moſt <hi>heinous Nature,</hi> and <hi>horrid Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence</hi> imaginable. But theſe are not the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of the preſent <hi>Compariſon</hi> between <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Judah;</hi> for 'tis <hi>Iſrael</hi> (as I ask'd leave to expreſs thoſe of the <hi>Romiſh Perſwaſion</hi>) under the unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs of their being ſeduced, and led out of the way; <hi>Revolted Iſrael, Iſrael</hi> under the <hi>Prejudice</hi> of <hi>falſe</hi> and <hi>corrupted Principles,</hi> under a kind of <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of being deceived,</hi> we are ſpeaking of; <hi>Iſrael too,</hi> made the Subject of the <hi>greateſt judgments.</hi> For what <hi>Hatred,</hi> what <hi>Scorn,</hi> what <hi>Diſgrace</hi> and <hi>Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment,</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:63910:18"/> have been thought too much for ſuch <hi>Offenders?</hi> Our <hi>Annals</hi> are full of their <hi>Story,</hi> our <hi>Laws</hi> moſt ſtrict and ſevere againſt them. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>ſuch,</hi> and <hi>Judah,</hi> i. e. <hi>thoſe</hi> who ſtill own the <hi>Purity of Religion,</hi> and the <hi>Principles</hi> thereof, <hi>thoſe</hi> who have ſeen what hath been done to ſuch <hi>Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minals,</hi> what <hi>they</hi> have ſuffered for <hi>their Wickedneſs,</hi> and yet make <hi>thoſe Principles</hi> a Covert for their Falſhood, <hi>thoſe Sufferings</hi> an Encouragement for themſelves to act <hi>greater Villanies;</hi> between <hi>ſuch</hi> I ſay, and <hi>Judah,</hi> hangs the Scale, and on theſe Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts muſt turn on her Side. For what will ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravate <hi>Sin</hi> if not its being committed againſt the general <hi>Principles, as of all Religion,</hi> ſo of <hi>what</hi> Men particularly profeſs, and the higheſt Profeſſions and Proteſtations to the contrary? What more <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to more dreadful Judgments</hi> than the hardening themſelves againſt ſo manifeſt and juſt an hand of God? as they have ſeen upon others in the like Guilt, and have felt upon themſelves, (an Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, one would think, that might work on them) in having their <hi>own</hi> ſo <hi>miraculouſly detected,</hi> and in ſome meaſure <hi>already puniſh'd.</hi> I ſpeak it not with Reſpect to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> thoſe of <hi>a corrupt</hi> and <hi>adulterated</hi> Religion, but, to give our <hi>modern Saints</hi> ſtill the <hi>Honour of the Compariſon,</hi> with reſpect to <hi>Judah;</hi> I ſpeak it too in vindication of the <hi>reformed Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:63910:19"/> the glorious ſtile whereof they ſo unjuſtly uſurp, and are ſo <hi>great a Scandal to.</hi> What, I ſay, will <hi>ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravate</hi> Sin, if not the continuing in it under ſuch Circumſtances? 'Twas the <hi>Horror</hi> of their Caſe in the Text, <hi>and</hi> ſo God himſelf enforces it, <hi>And I ſaw, when for all the Cauſes, whereby back-ſliding</hi> Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael <hi>committed Adultery, I had put her away, and given her a Bill of Divorce, yet her treacherous Siſter</hi> Judah <hi>feared not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What remains, is, that</p>
            <p>5. We ſum up all by way of Inference.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Uſe</hi> 1. From hence it appears, why in <hi>Scripture Treaſon</hi> and <hi>Rebellion</hi> are repreſented under <hi>ſo black a Character;</hi> as being <hi>a Sin</hi> which equals the worſt <hi>of Murders,</hi> ſuppoſes the ſame <hi>Rancor</hi> of Mind, ariſes from the ſame <hi>Paſſions</hi> of <hi>Avarice</hi> or <hi>Ambition,</hi> and in the <hi>fatal Conſequence of it,</hi> muſt end in <hi>Ruine,</hi> and that <hi>ſuch</hi> as carries the immediate <hi>marks of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Vengeance</hi> along with it; for with reference to all theſe St. <hi>Jude</hi> denounces the Woe, <hi>v. 11. Woe unto them, for they have gone in the way of</hi> Cain, <hi>and ran greedily after the Error</hi> of Balaam <hi>for Reward, and periſhed in the Gainſaying of</hi> Core: And long before <hi>Samuel had told Saul</hi> ('twas in his particular <hi>Caſe of Diſobedience,</hi> and that upon the moſt ſpecious <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Piety and high Devotion,</hi> out of a <hi>ſeeming Zeal for God's Honour,</hi> that he who gave him the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:63910:19"/> might himſelf by <hi>Sacrifice</hi> ſhare in the Spoil; 1 <hi>Sam. 15. 15. The People ſpared the beſt of the Sheep and of the Oxen, to ſacrifice unto the Lord</hi>) but appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable to the <hi>ſame Sin</hi> wherever 'tis found: <hi>Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion is as the Sin of Witchcraft, and Stubbornneſs is as Iniquity and Idolatry;</hi> and that will carry in it theſe <hi>ſeveral Aggravations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. 'Tis a <hi>Sin</hi> that in <hi>its exciting Cauſe</hi> uſually ſprings from <hi>Pride</hi> and <hi>Diſcontent;</hi> the very <hi>Sin</hi> of <hi>the Devil</hi> in Heaven it ſelf.</p>
            <p n="2">2. 'Tis a <hi>Sin</hi> that ſuppoſes the renouncing <hi>of God</hi> and <hi>his Religion.</hi> Whatever we may pretend otherwiſe, 'tis the very <hi>unchriſtning</hi> the Man, the <hi>drawing him off</hi> from his very <hi>Vow of Baptiſm,</hi> whereby he profeſſes to <hi>renounce the Devil and all his Works, the Pomps and Vanities of this wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed World;</hi> from the <hi>Obedience</hi> he then profeſſed to <hi>Chriſt</hi> his <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>General;</hi> 'tis the being aſhamed <hi>of his Croſs,</hi> and what the ſad conſequence thereof is.</p>
            <p n="3">3. 'Tis a <hi>Sin</hi> that puts us out of <hi>God's Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection;</hi> out of the <hi>Care</hi> of his <hi>Wiſdom</hi> and <hi>Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence;</hi> and no wonder, that being abandoned to <hi>our ſelves</hi> and the <hi>Devil</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. We ſhould be ſtill hurried (another fatal Attendant of this Guilt) from one <hi>degree of Wickedneſs</hi> to another, that we ſhould be ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:63910:20"/> by its <hi>bewitching Charms</hi> (ſuch as the <hi>High Out-cries</hi> for <hi>Liberty, Property,</hi> or <hi>Religion,</hi> (whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there be any reaſon for it or no) led on by <hi>Fears</hi> and <hi>Jealouſies</hi> (the proper <hi>Symptoms</hi> of thoſe who <hi>deal with the Devil</hi>) to all manner of Impieties. And ſo the latter Clauſe of that fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mention'd 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15. 15. imports, which tells us, that <hi>Stubbornneſs</hi> is as <hi>Iniquity</hi> and <hi>Idolatry: Iniquity,</hi> as it oppoſes whatſoever is <hi>juſt</hi> and <hi>equal</hi> in the <hi>Laws of Men; Idolatry,</hi> as it ſets up the <hi>Imagination of the Fool,</hi> the fine <hi>Model</hi> and <hi>Platform</hi> he bewitches himſelf with, the <hi>Idol</hi> of his own <hi>creating,</hi> in the <hi>place</hi> of God.</p>
            <p n="5">5. 'Tis a <hi>Sin, Witchcraft</hi> is, (and if <hi>Rebellion</hi> be ſuch it muſt take the <hi>ſame Fate</hi>) that muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>hope for Succeſs; Witchcraft</hi> puts the <hi>Wretch</hi> out of the <hi>Protection of Heaven,</hi> and cannot expect its <hi>Bleſſing.</hi> And this alone, one would think, ſhould be enough to diſparage the <hi>mad Attempts of the Rebel,</hi> that as <hi>Gowry</hi> is ſaid to have made his Remark, when he was <hi>hatching his Treaſon, that no Conſpiracy was ever ſo form'd amongſt all that he had met with, as not to be defective in one Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance or other,</hi> (and therefore <hi>he</hi> would take care to out-do them all) and needs it muſt be ſo; for it can never take <hi>God into the Counſel,</hi> never have the <hi>Help of his Wiſdom</hi> and <hi>Providence</hi> to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:63910:20"/> it: a ſhrewd <hi>Defect</hi> indeed, and ſuch a Circumſtance, as might ſerve to recover Men to their Wits, if any thing were ſufficient to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover <hi>him</hi> who is ſo <hi>bewitch'd</hi> with his own <hi>Pride, Malice,</hi> or <hi>Revenge,</hi> ſome of the neceſſary Ingredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents in this <hi>Sorcery:</hi> and what is ſtill more dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful than all this,</p>
            <p n="6">6. 'Tis <hi>a Sin</hi> that ſhall be eternally puniſh'd with that <hi>Despair in Hell,</hi> with which 'tis begun, and proſecuted on <hi>Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Uſe</hi> 2. From hence ſee the many and great Reaſons we have to deteſt the <hi>execrable Treaſon</hi> of this Day. <hi>Tell it not in</hi> Gath, <hi>publiſh it not in</hi> Askelon: That ever <hi>Religion</hi> ſhould be proſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted to ſerve ſo <hi>great a Villany!</hi> That the <hi>Holy Name of God</hi> ſhould be made uſe of to counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance the <hi>Murdering</hi> of his own Vicegerent. 'Twas <hi>David</hi>'s Queſtion to the <hi>Amalekite,</hi> who might have pleaded the Royal Command of <hi>Saul,</hi> and but a ſort of Allegiance paid to him in his Anguiſh, to ſtand upon him and ſlay him, 2 <hi>Sam. 1. 14. How waſt thou not afraid to ſtretch forth thine hand to deſtroy the Lord's Anointed?</hi> Is it nothing to have the <hi>Divine Character</hi> effaced? Nothing to be guilty of Royal Blood? To <hi>behead the Nation at a Blow,</hi> and then bring him <hi>by whom
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:63910:21"/> Kings reign,</hi> into the Conſpiracy? <hi>Bleſſed Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our!</hi> Was this thy meaning when thou com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandedſt to <hi>give to Caeſar the things that are Caeſars?</hi> Was this the <hi>Reaſon of thy ſubmitting to Civil Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> that <hi>thy Diſciples</hi> muſt preſently conſtrue it, to ſignifie <hi>their Right to depoſe them?</hi> Or, was it <hi>for this Thou</hi> inſpired'ſt good St. <hi>Paul</hi> to tell us, <hi>We muſt needs be ſubject not only for Wrath but Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi> ſake, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 5. that for <hi>Conſcience</hi> ſake we ſhould Rebell againſt them? I might far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther aggravate the <hi>Fact,</hi> from the <hi>Excellency</hi> of the <hi>Perſon, his Clemency, his Juſtice, his Temperance, his Chaſtity, his exemplary Piety</hi> and <hi>Patience;</hi> but 'tis too <hi>ſtupifying an Argument</hi> to dwell on; and therefore ſhall only add <hi>this,</hi> that the <hi>only way</hi> not to make all this <hi>horrid Guilt ours,</hi> is that which God predicts, as what muſt lead to the Recovery of <hi>Iſrael</hi> from that <hi>Captivity</hi> their <hi>Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion</hi> brought upon them; which ſhall be my laſt Uſe; <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Uſe</hi> 3. A <hi>turning to God, and</hi> (for they muſt go together) <hi>to our King;</hi> ſo 'tis <hi>Hoſea 3. 5. After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſhall the Children of Iſrael return, and ſeek the Lord their God, and</hi> David <hi>their King.</hi> There is a <hi>ſort of Allegiance,</hi> there <hi>is a Duty</hi> we can ſtill pay to the <hi>Royal Martyr;</hi> what was wanting to <hi>his Perſon</hi> let us pay to his <hi>Memory,</hi> rather let us pay
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:63910:21"/> to <hi>what of him ſurvives,</hi> our <hi>Dear Sovereign;</hi> for He too <hi>ſuffer'd in</hi> and <hi>with him.</hi> Let us conſider, <hi>who</hi> 'twas that ſet either <hi>Father</hi> or <hi>Son on the Throne,</hi> and let us not forget to pay all <hi>Duty and Allegiance</hi> there: 'tis the only Method left us to redeem <hi>the Nation,</hi> and make the Stain <hi>of the Guilt</hi> not <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick</hi> ſtill. Let us above all <hi>diſclaim the Principles</hi> on which 'twas acted: let neither <hi>Iſrael</hi> nor <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah, Religion</hi> under any Name whatever, ſo <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hallow</hi> it ſelf, as to juſtifie the <hi>leaſt Degree of Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> 'Tis a Debt we all owe <hi>to the Honour of our great Maſter's Name,</hi> which hath ſo much ſuffer'd <hi>on either hand,</hi> as to take care that that be no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger thus <hi>reproached;</hi> for thus to diſhonour <hi>him</hi> and <hi>his</hi> Goſpel, certainly is more than to <hi>crucifie him afreſh;</hi> 'tis to make <hi>him</hi> the very <hi>Malefactor on the Croſs,</hi> to make him the <hi>Barabbas,</hi> the Author of <hi>Sedition</hi> and <hi>Murder;</hi> in the greateſt <hi>Deteſtation</hi> and <hi>Abhorrence</hi> whereof, give me leave to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude with the Words of the Apoſtle, <hi>Wherefore you muſt needs be ſubject.</hi> 'Tis the Duty, as <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,</hi> we owe to that <hi>Holy Name;</hi> 'tis the <hi>trueſt Honour</hi> you can do the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> to free it from <hi>thoſe Abuſes</hi> to which <hi>turbulent</hi> and <hi>ſeditious</hi> Men proſtitute that <hi>Holy, Heavenly, and Peaceable Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</hi> You are <hi>thoſe who your ſelves expect Crowns,</hi> ('tis the Name under which <hi>the future Glory you
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:63910:22" rendition="simple:additions"/> hope for</hi> is expreſs'd) and is the <hi>Rebel</hi> fit to be <hi>advanced to that Dignity?</hi> you expect an <hi>everlaſting Kingdom,</hi> think not a little <hi>Patience</hi> and <hi>Subjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> too much to pay for it: you look <hi>after Eternal Joy,</hi> let not <hi>Repining</hi> and <hi>Murmuring</hi> be the <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratives for it!</hi> Submit to <hi>thoſe whom the Lord hath ſet over you;</hi> 'Tis your undoubted <hi>Duty,</hi> and 'tis your <hi>Reward:</hi> your <hi>Reward here,</hi> in that <hi>Peace,</hi> that <hi>Quiet,</hi> that <hi>Content,</hi> (and what doth not that Name contain?) which ſuch a <hi>Temper</hi> leads to, and enjoys at preſent; and 'twill be your <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> hereafter in that <hi>State of everlaſting and unal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terable Obedience</hi> to the <hi>King of Kings,</hi> in which <hi>Heaven</hi> and its <hi>Happineſs</hi> will conſiſt.</p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Now unto the King Eternal, Immortal, Inviſible, the only Wiſe God, be Honour and Glory for ever, and ever, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>☞ <hi>England</hi>'s Black Tribunal: Containing the Tryal of the Bleſſed Martyr-King <hi>Charles</hi> I. with the Dying Speeches and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour of many of the Nobility and Gentry who ſuffered Death for their Loyalty by the then Rebels. Sold by <hi>Henry Playford</hi> near the <hi>Temple-Church.</hi> 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. Price bound 2 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:63910:22"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
